Guide to the New York Hard Hat News Records WAG.212
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
New York Hard Hat News Records
1958-2002
1988-2002
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
New York Hard Hat News
LaTour, Jane
Robinson, Guy
WAG.212
10.7 Linear Feet in 7 record cartons and two oversize flat boxes.
8.5 Megabytes in 50 computer files
The New York Hard Hat News was a quarterly newspaper primarily for construction workers in the New York metropolitan area, published between 1989-1993 and 1997-2002. The newsletter covered topics of concern to workers in the building trades, with an emphasis on efforts to increase union democracy, job site safety, and combat corruption in labor unions and in the construction industry. The New York Hard Hat News Records date between 1958 and 2002, with the bulk of the material created between 1988 and 2002. The collection contains paper and born-digital materials created and assembled by editors Jane LaTour and Guy Robinson in order to prepare and print the newsletter, including clippings, research files, correspondence, drafts, and administrative files.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Jane LaTour and Guy Robinson, 2002. The accession number associated with this gift is 2002.036.
Arrangement
The paper materials in this collection have not been arranged by an archivist, except where it was necessary to rehouse oversize material into appropriately sized housing. The remaining paper materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor. Related born-digital material and paper material have been arranged together intellectually.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical Note
The New York Hard Hat News was a quarterly newspaper primarily for construction workers in the New York metropolitan area, published between 1989-1993 and 1997-2002. The newsletter covered topics of concern to workers in the building trades, with an emphasis on efforts to increase union democracy, job site safety, and combat corruption in labor unions and in the construction industry. The New York Hard Hat News was started in 1989 by Dan Gilroy, with Guy Robinson taking over as editor in 1992. Both Gilroy and Robinson were members of the Union Brotherhood of Carpenters Local Union 608 in New York City. The newsletter was revived in 1997 by Robinson and Jane LaTour. LaTour is a journalist and labor activist in New York City.
Scope and Contents
The New York Hard Hat News Records document the work of editors Jane LaTour and Guy Robinson to publish the newsletter. The collection contains editorial files, clippings, research files, correspondence, drafts, issues of the New York Hard Hat News, and administrative files. The collection dates between 1941 and 2002, with the bulk of the material created between 1993 and 2002. Materials include clippings from mainstream and labor periodicals, paper and born-digital drafts and publication ready articles written for the New York Hard Hat News, correspondence between the editors and writers, research materials for articles, and general research files maintained by Robinson. The editorial files include material gathered and created for individual issues, notebooks containing research and article material, and editorial policies. Robinson's research files contain information on general labor issues in New York City and nationwide, specific trades, labor unions, and corruption in labor unions and the construction industry. Contributor files are listed by contributor name and contain correspondence and drafts of articles. The collection also includes grant applications, meeting agenda and minutes, financial documents, and scanned images used in the newsletter.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
An access terminal for born-digital materials in the collection is available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Researchers may view an item's original container and/or carrier, but the physical carriers themselves are not available for use because of preservation concerns.
Related Materials
Issues of the New York Hard Hat News published between 1998 and 2002 are held in the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives under call number HD6515.B89 N49.
Appraisal
Duplicate clippings and publications were deaccessioned.
Labor unions -- New York (State); Labor unions -- Corrupt practices -- New York (State); Building trades -- New York (State) -- New York; Construction industry -- Labor unions -- United States.; Labor journalism -- New York (State) -- New York.; Labor union democracy -- New York (State) -- New York.; Newsletters -- Publishing -- United States.; LaTour, Jane; Robinson, Guy; Gilroy, Dan; LaTour, Jane; Robinson, Guy
- Advertisers, 1995-1999 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Articles on New York Hard Hat News, 1992-2001 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Background and potential stories, 1995-2000 (Box 2, Folder 15-17, Box 8, Folder 9)
- Belson, Bruce, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 27)
- Construction Organizing Membership Education Training (COMET), 1993-1997 (Box 2, Folder 29-31, Box 8, Folder 9)
- Contacts, Undated (Box 7, Folder 24)
- Correspondence, 1988-2002 (Box 1, Folder 12-18, Box 2, Folder 11-14, Box 4, Folder 1-2, Folder 39, Box 6, Folder 16, Folder 83, Box 8, Folder 9)
- Cylich, Bernie, 1990-1991 (Box 6, Folder 19)
- Development research, 1996-2000 (Box 1, Folder 26-29)
- Editorial files, 1988-2002; 322.6 kilobytes in 37 computer files (Box 1, Folder 1-2, Folder 5-11, Box 2, Folder 18, Box 4, Folder 3-37, Box 5, Folder 2, Folder 72, Box 6, Folder 13-15, Folder 85-87, Box 7, Folder 1-18, Box 8, Folder 1-5, Box Shared Tamiment MSXOS004, Folder 5-6, Box Electronic records, Object TW_WAG_212_ER_1, Object TW_WAG_212_ER_7, Object TW_WAG_212_ER_8, Object TW_WAG_212_ER_9)
- Editorial meetings, 1989-1991 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Engel, Barry, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 34)
- Financial records, 1989-2002 (Box 1, Folder 30-32, Box 4, Folder 38, Box 6, Folder 9)
- Fitch, Bob, 1996-1997 (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
- Gilroy, Dan, 1990-1995 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Grant files, 1989-2001 (Box 1, Folder 35, Box 2, Folder 1-9, Box 6, Folder 7, Box 7, Folder 42)
- Graphics, 1984-1999; 8.2 Megabytes in 13 computer files (Box 1, Folder 24, Box 6, Folder 84, Box 7, Folder 21-22, Box Electronic records, Object TW_WAG_212_ER_2, Object TW_WAG_212_ER_11, Object TW_WAG_212_ER_13, Object TW_WAG_212_ER_12, Object TW_WAG_212_ER_10, Object TW_WAG_212_ER_3, Object TW_WAG_212_ER_4, Object TW_WAG_212_ER_5, Object TW_WAG_212_ER_6)
- Hanahan, Thomas, 1989-1990 (Box 5, Folder 56-58)
- Harte, John, 1989 (Box 7, Folder 25)
- Huck/Kononpaki Cartoons, 1990-1993 (Box 4, Folder 40, Box 5, Folder 1)
- Journalism standards, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Keough, Jim, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 23)
- Kirkland, John, 1988-1989 (Box 6, Folder 26)
- LaTour, Jane -- Notebooks, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 34)
- Letters of support, 1997-1998 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Mailing lists, Undated (Box 6, Folder 56)
- McMurray, Frank, 1987-1990 (Box 7, Folder 26)
- McNamara, James F., 1982-1990 (Box 6, Folder 21)
- Meeting agendas and minutes, 1997-1998 (Box 1, Folder 19-20)
- Moffatt, Bill, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 20)
- Murphy, Michael E., 1989-1992 (Box 6, Folder 10-12, Box 7, Folder 28-30)
- Newsletter production, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 23)
- Printing information, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Promotional material, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Research files -- 42nd Street redevelopment, 1985-1990 (Box 6, Folder 66, Box 8, Folder 13)
- Research files -- 1991 contracts, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 40)
- Research files -- A.L.L. Partitions, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 58)
- Research files -- America's working man, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 77)
- Research files -- American Labor, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 59)
- Research files -- Anti-Homeport, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 41)
- Research files -- Apprentice information, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 39)
- Research files -- Asbestos, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 17, Box Shared Tamiment MSXOS004, Folder 1)
- Research files -- Asbestos and White Lung Association, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 42)
- Research files -- Association for Union Democracy, 1981-1994 (Box 5, Folder 9, Box 6, Folder 82, Box 7, Folder 41)
- Research files -- Bruce & Bruce Scenery employee policy, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 24)
- Research files -- Building trades, 1987-1991 (Box 5, Folder 29, Box 6, Folder 54-55)
- Research files -- Bureau of Labor Statistics, 1985-1989 (Box 5, Folder 27-28)
- Research files -- California Hard Hat News and Hard Hat Times, 1987-1990 (Box 7, Folder 19)
- Research files -- Canadian and American market recovery, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 45)
- Research files -- Carey, Ron, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 34)
- Research files -- Carpenters, 1983-2002 (Box 3, Folder 15-17, Box 5, Folder 32, Box 6, Folder 32-39, Box 7, Folder 36-38, Box 8, Folder 6)
- Research files -- Carpenters for a Stronger Union, 1983-1990 (Box 6, Folder 6, Box 7, Folder 27)
- Research files -- Changing Work, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 71)
- Research files -- Chinese-American Planning Council and Wing Lam, 1989-1991 (Box 7, Folder 40)
- Research files -- City of New York Department of Housing Preservation and Development, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Research files -- Construction industry, 1958-2002 (Box 2, Folder 19-26, Box 6, Folder 61-62, Box 8, Folder 6, Box Shared Tamiment MSXOS004, Folder 1-2)
- Research files -- Contracting figures, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Research files -- Contractors, 1998-2001 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Research files -- Corruption, 2000-2002 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Research files -- Corruption and organized crime, 1989 (Box 8, Folder 11)
- Research files -- Crane collapses, 1989-1990 (Box 6, Folder 69)
- Research files -- Crime, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 68)
- Research files -- Daily News strike, 1991 (Box 8, Folder 12)
- Research files -- Davis-Bacon Act, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Research files -- Dilemma in the Millennium: Capital Needs of the World's Capitol City, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 26-33)
- Research files -- Double breasting, 1985-1991 (Box 6, Folder 72)
- Research files -- Drywall Tapers of Greater New York, Local 1974, et al. v. Local 530, Operative Plasterers and Association, et al., 1990 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Research files -- Durcan, Jack, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 33)
- Research files -- Dust, 1989-1990 (Box 5, Folder 37-38)
- Research files -- Eastern Airlines, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 75, Box 8, Folder 13)
- Research files -- Ecology, 1989 (Box 8, Folder 10)
- Research files -- Economics, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Research files -- Economics, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 43)
- Research files -- Ehrlich, Mark, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 22)
- Research files -- Electricians, 1985-1999 (Box 3, Folder 19, Box 6, Folder 40-41, Box 8, Folder 1-2)
- Research files -- Employee Retirement Income Security Act (ERISA) and Labor-Management Reporting and Disclosure Act (LMRDA), 1979-1989 (Box 6, Folder 70-71)
- Research files -- Fellner, Kim, In search of the movement: 1960s activists in labor, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 69)
- Research files -- Fiberglass, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 44)
- Research files -- Grand Central, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 23)
- Research files -- General labor and labor unions material, 1980-1989 (Box 6, Folder 80)
- Research files -- Gulf War, 1990-1991 (Box 5, Folder 55)
- Research files -- Harrington, Mike, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 18)
- Research files -- Hazardous materials, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 20)
- Research files -- Health and safety, 1988-2002 (Box 3, Folder 6-8, Folder 13-14, Box 5, Folder 19, Box 8, Folder 9, Box Shared Tamiment MSXOS004, Folder 3)
- Research files -- Healthcare reform, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 68)
- Research files -- Hell on Wheels, 1985-1990 (Box 5, Folder 14-15, Box 8, Folder 8)
- Research files -- House wreckers, 1985-1989 (Box 6, Folder 57)
- Research files -- Housing, 1987-1997 (Box 3, Folder 2, Box 6, Folder 63, Box Shared Tamiment MSXOS004, Folder 1)
- Research files -- Immigration, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 24)
- Research files -- International Falls, Minnesota, 1989-1990 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Research files -- International unions, 1988-1989 (Box 6, Folder 67, Box 8, Folder 13)
- Research files -- Ironworkers, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 42-43)
- Research files -- John F. Kennedy International Airport 2000 project, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 35)
- Research files -- Kuwait, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 60)
- Research files -- Labor archives, union democracy, carpenters, 1998-1999 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Research files -- Labor Militant construction program, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 67, Box 8, Folder 7)
- Research files -- Labor publications, 1988-1989 (Box 5, Folder 25)
- Research files -- Labor Punchout, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 32)
- Research files -- Labor Solidarity Network, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 18)
- Research files -- Laborers, 1994-1999 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Research files -- Laborers International Union of North America and organized crime, 1986-1988 (Box 6, Folder 28)
- Research files -- Lathers, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 52)
- Research files -- Mail handlers, 1989-1990 (Box 6, Folder 44)
- Research files -- Mason tenders, 1985-1989 (Box 6, Folder 51)
- Research files -- Massachusetts labor support project, 1986-1988 (Box 6, Folder 79)
- Research files -- Minority coalition, 1989-1990 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Research files -- Mixed clippings, notes, and publications, 1989-1994 (Box 7, Folder 46-54, Box Shared Tamiment MSXOS004, Folder 6)
- Research files -- Mixed publications, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 47-53, Box 8, Folder 7-8)
- Research files -- Mob activity and carpenters, 1989-1991 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Research files -- Moscatiello, Louis D., indictment, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 30-31)
- Research files -- National Labor Relations Act, 1987-1988 (Box 5, Folder 26)
- Research files -- National Market Recovery Handbook for Union Construction, 1984-1985 (Box 5, Folder 73)
- Research files -- New Directions for Labor conferences, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 54)
- Research files -- New York City Central Labor Council, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 49)
- Research files -- New York City District Council of the United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners Racketeer Influenced and Corrupt Organizations Act (RICO) suit, 1981-1991 (Box 5, Folder 62-66)
- Research files -- New York City real estate, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 59)
- Research files -- New York City water project, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 61)
- Research files -- New York Committee for Occupational Safety and Health (NYCOSH), 1989 (Box 6, Folder 76)
- Research files -- New York Tradeswomen, 1988-1989 (Box 5, Folder 22, Folder 57)
- Research files -- Non-union jobs, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Research files -- Operating engineers, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 50, Box 8, Folder 1)
- Research files -- Painters, 1989-1990 (Box 6, Folder 3, Folder 46-47, Box 8, Folder 6)
- Research files -- Paper workers boycott, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Research files -- Pensions, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 78)
- Research files -- Pick & Shovel, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 29)
- Research files -- Plasterers, 1989-1990 (Box 6, Folder 45, Box 8, Folder 6)
- Research files -- Plumbers, 1993-1997 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Research files -- Plumbers and Pipefitters, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 30-31)
- Research files -- Port Authority, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Research files -- Poverty, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 45)
- Research files -- Prevailing wage, 1995-2002 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Research files -- Privatization and transportation, 1996-1997 (Box 3, Folder 3-4, Box Shared Tamiment MSXOS004, Folder 4)
- Research files -- Productivity in construction, 1979-1989 (Box 5, Folder 21)
- Research files -- Public housing, 1984-1991 (Box 6, Folder 81, Box 8, Folder 5)
- Research files -- Racism, 1989 (Box 8, Folder 10)
- Research files -- Rivera, Dennis, 1990-1991 (Box 5, Folder 74)
- Research files -- Roofers, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 23-24)
- Research files -- Sheet metal workers, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 22, Box 6, Folder 53)
- Research files -- Soloway, Irene, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 17)
- Research files -- Souvenir programs, 1999-2000 (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Research files -- Stanford, Catherine M.; Labor Notes; Rank and File Network, 1989 (Box 7, Folder 20)
- Research files -- TAP Electrical Contracting Service, International Brotherhood of Teamsters Local 363, and International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers Local 3, 1977-1990 (Box 6, Folder 60)
- Research files -- Teamsters, 1985-2000 (Box 2, Folder 10, Box 5, Folder 36, Box 6, Folder 48)
- Research files -- Temporary workers, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Research files -- Unemployed committees, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Research files -- Union busting, 1979-1980 (Box 6, Folder 73-74)
- Research files -- Union meetings, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 46)
- Research files -- Union publications, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 7, Box 8, Folder 5)
- Research files -- Veteran's Administration, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 43)
- Research files -- Wage Slave World News, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Research files -- Wages, 1991-2000 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Research files -- Water meter scandal, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 70)
- Research files -- Wicks Law, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 44)
- Research files -- Workers' compensation and Occupational Safety and Health Administration (OSHA), 1987-2000 (Box 3, Folder 11-12, Box 6, Folder 64-65)
- Ruderman, Evan, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 35)
- Shepperson, Willie, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 31)
- Subscription forms, 1988-1993 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Walters, Bill, 1989-1992 (Box 6, Folder 25)
- Zeigler, Henry, 1988-1989 (Box 7, Folder 33)
- Zeluck, Barbara, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 39)